In 2014, the qualifying exam for the US Physics Team had this as question 19:
2014年，美国物理竞赛队，资格考试的第19题是这个：
A helicopter is flying horizontally at constant speed.
一架直升飞机正在匀速平飞
A perfectly flexible uniform cable is suspended beneath the helicopter.
一条可以任意弯曲的均质缆绳悬挂在直升机下方
Air friction on the cable is not negligible.
线缆所受的空气阻力不可忽略
So, which of the following diagrams best shows the shape of the cable
当直升机在空中向右飞行时
as the helicopter flies through the air to the right?
下面哪个图示最符合缆绳的形状
Is it A. hanging straight down.
是选A——竖直向下？
B, hanging diagonally to the left?
B——朝向左下的直线？
C, this hook shape.
C——鱼钩状？
D, the inverted hook shape,
D——翻转的鱼钩状？
or E, a kind of S bend.
还是E选项——类似S形？
Now, apparently there 's been a certain amount of controversy
人们对这个问题的正确答案众说纷纭
about the correct answer to this question.
So, today we're gonna go up in this helicopter,
所以今天  我们要坐上直升机
and put this question to rest once and for all.
来彻底终结这个问题
Let's go.
走起
I've got several thousand hours of carrying sling loads,
我吊运货物已有数千小时的经验
fire buckets,
消防水桶
concrete buckets, doing power line construction, actual power poles.
混凝土桶  在电网建设时用来造电线杆
You name it, anything that needs to be moved around the mountains,
你叫得上名字的、一切需要在山间运输的东西
I 've done.
我都做过
Biggest concern that I have is that the rope's gonna interact with the rotor wash
我最担心的是，绳子会与下洗流发生作用
as its interaction with the ambient air around the aircraft.
毕竟旋翼会影响飞机周围环境的空气
And we'll get a whipping action
这可能会导致鞭鞘效应
that falls down the rope and flips around on the end
沿缆绳一路向下传  把末端甩起来
to a point that we worry if it will have a tendency
我们怕末端会甩得越来越高
to work its way back up towards the aircraft.
Obviously, we don't want it getting in the rotors or the tail rotor.
我们当然不希望它缠上旋翼或尾翼
- [Derek] Alright, we're all set.
准备好了
Movin' up.
起飞
Here I'm deploying a battle rope, like you'd see at the gym.
我搞了条你会健身房里见到的那种战斗绳
This one is about 15 meters long
这条有15米长
and it weighs 20 kilograms.
重量有20千克
- [Craig] See, the whipping action's begun.
开始有鞭鞘效应了
- [Derek] I see it.
看到了
So, if we go really slow, will we avoid that?
我们试试走得非常慢  能不能避免这种现象
- We 'll see.
看着吧
We'll see where the rotor wash stops interacting with the rope
看看下洗流何时会不再影响绳子和环境气流
and the ambient wind.
Now the setup looks pretty simple, but few people agree on what the right answer should be.
题目条件看似非常简单  但关于正确答案人们却莫衷一是
When I polled YouTube,
我在 YouTube 上发布投票的时候
the most common answer was C.
最常见的选项是 C
Well done on making that beautiful bell curve by the way.
顺便一提  这条钟型曲线画得漂亮
We got in touch with the question's author,
我们和问题的提出者 Paul Stanley 教授
Professor Paul Stanley.
取得了联系
There was some creative students who actually constructed
有些异想天开的学生其实已经构造了
their own homemade scenarios.
他们自己的模拟场景
One had a fan to the side
侧面有一个风扇
and another fan blowing downward
另一个风扇从上往下吹
so that they could mimic the motion of the helicopter
这样他们就能模拟直升机的运动
and suspended a string and said, "Oh, it's this design."
然后在上面悬挂一条绳子  他们说  噢  就是这样
And the faculty members looked at it and said,
我们的教授看到之后说
" Oh , obviously I can prove that the answer is this answer."
哦  显然我能证明这个就是正确答案
They just didn't agree with each other.
但他们之间的意见却不能统一
- If we approximated as a chain of rigid links
- 如果我们把它近似看作一串相互连接的刚体
- I don't think you can just do that.
- 我不觉得你能那么做
- What do you think?
- 你怎么看
- I think you're more likely to be C.
- 我觉得答案更像是 C
- I think it is D. - D?
- 我觉得是 D - D
- My guess is B.
- 我猜是 B
- What do you think? - B. - B?
- 你觉得呢 - B - B
- Imma go with A.
- 我支持 A
- Interestingly, no one chose E.
- 有趣的是 没人选择 E
Have you locked in your prediction?
你锁定你的选项了吗
To make sure the rope doesn't come up into the rotors of the helicopter,
为了保证绳子不被卷进直升机的螺旋桨
pilot Craig wanted to keep the rope on our right side
飞行员 Craig 让我们把绳子放在右侧
so he could keep an eye on it.
方便他多加留意
Looks pretty good.
看起来不错
- I'm trying to make it look good.
- 我正在试着让它保持稳定
I mean I'm really working on it.
我的意思是我很努力了
- You're working hard.
- 辛苦你了
So, we're not going straight forward.
我们不会向正前方飞行
We're actually going diagonally forward and to the left.
实际上我们在往左前方运动
But you can clearly see the rope is hanging straight,
但是你能明显看到悬挂的绳子
diagonally to the left.
是一条向左的斜直线
That's a pretty good diagonal, man.
哇哦  完美的斜线
So, the correct answer to the question is B.
所以  正确答案是 B
You wanna pull it in?
你要把它收回来么？
- Up it comes.
在收了
- [Derek] We're going to try a few more experiments,
我们准备多尝试几个实验
adding a weight to the end of the rope and then a parachute.
比如在绳子末端加点配重或者降落伞什么的
But first I want to discuss why the answer is B.
但首先我想先解释一下为什么答案是B
There are two external forces acting on the rope,
绳子受到2个外力
gravity pulling it down and air resistance to the left.
分别是向下的重力和向左的空气阻力
When flying along at constant speed,
当飞机匀速飞行时
these forces must be perfectly balanced by the tension in the rope.
这两个力必须与绳子的张力  形成受力平衡
Now, when I set out to do this experiment,
刚开始的时候
I wondered if the rope would be affected by the air pushed down by the helicopters rotor,
我很好奇绳子会不会受到旋翼产生的向下气流影响
but judging by our results.
但是从实验结果来看
This was not the case.
完全没影响
- The rotor wash doesn't extend down below the helicopter,
机翼产生的洗流不会延伸到直升机的下方
all that far. It dissipates pretty quickly.
它衰减得非常快
- So, you can consider the air resistance on the rope
因此  可以认为绳子受到的空气阻力
as entirely due to its motion through still air.
完全是由于它在静止的空气中运动
Imagine dividing the rope up into many short sections.
想象一下  将绳子分成很多小段
Each section has the same weight and experiences the same amount of air resistance
每一段的质量与其受到的空气阻力都相同
because it has the same cross-sectional area.
因为各段的截面积相同
And it's moving at the same speed.
并且运动速度一致
Now, the tension in any section of the rope
每一段绳子受到的拉力
must balance the sum of the air resistance
必须平衡空气阻力
and weight of all the sections beneath it.
以及下方所有绳子施加给它的总拉力
So, the tension is zero at the bottom of the rope,
因此  绳子末端受到的合力为0
and it increases linearly up to a maximum at the top.
并且以线性递增  在顶端达到最大值
You can see the tension is small at the bottom of the rope, and that's why it wiggles around
由于绳子末端的拉力很小  因此它会产生摆动
while the top is much steadier.
而顶部则更稳定
Now, although the magnitude of tension changes throughout the rope,
虽然整个绳子受到的拉力大小会发生变化
it's direction doesn't.
但是方向并没有变
And that's because the ratio of air resistance
因为绳子各处  所受空气阻力与重力的比值都相同
to weight is the same at every point along the rope.
That is why a uniform flexible cable hangs in a straight diagonal line
这就是为什么当直升机拖着柔性绳子做匀速运动时
when pulled at constant speed by a helicopter.
绳子会竖直地挂在直升机上
If the helicopter flies faster,
如果直升机运动得更快
the angle of the rope changes, but it still makes a diagonal straight line
绳子与飞机面不再呈直角  但绳子仍然是直的
because the ratio of air resistance to weight
因为绳子上的每一点  所受的空气阻力和重力  比值仍然相同
is still constant along the entire length of the rope.
But this got me wondering, "What would happen if we added a weight
但是这让我很好奇  如果我们给绳子末端加上配重
to the end of the rope?"
会发生什么呢
Here, I have a 20 pound, that's an eight or nine kilos kettlebell.
这有一个重20磅  大约8到9千克的壶铃
And I want to ask you to make a prediction.
我想请你预测一下
What shape do you think the rope will make now?
这个绳子会是什么形状
Will it still be that diagonal,
它依然会是斜线吗
or will it be one of the other five options?
还是说  会变成剩下四种情况之一
One more question for you.
再问你一个问题
If we chucked a weight at the bottom,
如果我们在末尾加一个配重
which shape would it be?
它会变成什么形状
- Oh. - Probably D.
哦  大概是 D
- B, or possibly C.
B  也可能是 C
- [Derek] Does that change it?
配重会改变绳子的形状吗
- Then I think it would be B.
我觉得会是 B
- Easy to do on the ground.
在地上还是容易拉上来的
好的  我们正在把绳子从这一侧放下去
这次的绳子末端有个重20磅的壶铃
底下吊着个大家伙  感觉如何
完全没在晃动
那行
你的手臂还好吗
我感觉不错  你懂的
我感觉这挺轻松的
等我收绳子的时候可就没这么轻松了
好  绳子已经下去了吧？ 是的
Okay, let's give it a shot.
行  那我们来试试看
Here the helicopter is flying at nearly a hundred kilometers per hour,
现在直升机以接近100千米的时速飞行
and the rope makes a different shape.
绳子呈现出一个不同的形状
You can clearly see, it looks like an inverted J.
你可以清楚地看到  它像个倒过来的 J
This is option D.
也就是选项D的样子
In fact, this is how the question on the qualifying exam originated.
实际上  这就是这道考试题目的来源
- So, I taught for a semester in Hong Kong,
我在香港教了一学期的课
and we'd go hiking in the New Territories.
那时候  我们会去新界远足
One of the times I was hiking,
有次出去远足的时候
I saw a helicopter fly with a cable beneath it.
我看见一架直升机  底下吊着一根绳子
It was carrying something to one of the remote parts
它当时正在运送什么东西
of the Hong Kong New Territories.
到新界的偏远地区
And I saw the shape of the cable and thought to myself,
我看着那绳子的形状  心想
"That looks a little counter intuitive and very neat.
“它看起来有点反直觉  而且非常巧妙
This might make a good multiple choice question
这可以用来出一道很棒的选择题
for the selection exam for the students."
放在学生的选拔考试里”
The cable that I saw had a weight hanging on the end,
我看到的那根绳子  末端吊着重物
which gave it a certain curved shape.
这使绳子呈现某种弯曲的形状
When I shared this with the other coaches, another coach,
当我把这件事分享给其他老师时  其中有一位
Andrew Linn, looked at it and said,
Andrew Linn  他看了一眼然后说
"I think the question might even be more fun
“我觉得这个问题可以更有趣一点
if there is no weight on the cable
如果绳子上什么都没有
because that is even harder to imagine."
因为这种情况更难想象”
- [Derek] To understand why the rope makes this shape,
要弄明白为什么绳子变成这个形状
we can use the same analysis as before.
我们可以用相同的分析方式
But now we need to add a large weight to the end of the rope.
但是这次我们得在绳子末端增加很多重量
And this means at the bottom, the tension needs to be almost vertical
这也就意味着  绳子末端的张力要几乎竖直
to support the weight of the kettlebell,
以平衡壶铃受的重力
which has a lot of weight but not much air resistance.
它很重  但是空气阻力不大
As you go up the rope, the ratio of total air resistance
从绳子的底端往上看  这个整体受到的空气阻力
to weight for everything beneath increases.
和它所受到重力的比例增加了
So, the rope turns more horizontal in order for the tension
所以  绳子不断向水平方向倾斜
to balance out that increasing air resistance.
使绳子的张力能与增加的空气阻力平衡
- You're more than halfway. You got it.
绳子已经上来一半了  你可以的
- [Derek] For the final test,
I wanted to add something to the bottom of the rope that added almost no weight, but significant air resistance.
So, I picked a Veritasium flag, of course.
So, what do you think about hanging this at the end of the rope?
- Well, it's all science experiment for me
'cause these are all the things you'd never do with a helicopter in a row.
- What would it be the real risks, like tail rotor or this rotor, or both?
- Either.
Any kind of this getting into the inner tail rotor
would be destruction to the aircraft.
And we 'll start,
here we go .
- [Derek] Now the rope still seems to be pretty straight.
I think it's because the flag
isn't actually adding much drag.
Still looks pretty crazy, interestingly.
So, we decided to add a small parachute to the end of the rope.
All right, let's try it.
The concern here was that the parachute
could get flipped up into the rotors during deployment.
So, we bundled the shoot up into a backpack.
- [Craig] Very nicely done.
- [Derek] Does it deploy more than that?
- [Craig] No, but once we start moving,
its gonna grab a lot of air.
- [Derek] Now, with the parachute at the end of the rope,
it makes a J shape, which is answer C.
With extra air resistance at the end of the rope,
but not much weight, the tension has to be virtually horizontal.
And then as you go up the rope,
the ratio of total air resistance to weight
for everything beneath decreases.
So, the rope becomes more vertical
to balance out the increasing weight.
So, depending on what's on the end of the rope,
you could get answers B , C or D.
Now, if you enjoyed this video, I bet you would also like my bullet block experiment series.
So, check it out.